An Inventory to the Pardee Lowe papers, 1911-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
- Correspondence, 1930s (Box 276)
  Including regarding submitting writings for publication, and printed reports and clippings
- Fundraising for China relief material, 1930s-1940s (Box 276)
- Relief work in the U.S., 1930s (Box 276)
- Philanthropic and social work activities (Box 276)
- Reports and clippings on development of the Sinotype machine for the composition of Chinese from a keyboard, 1959 (Box 276)
  See also box 193.
- U.S. Educational Foundation in Nanking, China assignment reports and files, 1948-1949 (Box 277-278.)
- Typescript memos from Taipei, Taiwan, 1961 (Box 278)
- Japanese Americans subject files, 1920s-1960s (Box 279)
- War Relocation of persons of Japanese ancestry reports and other government documents, 1940s (Box 279)
- Subject files on Japan, 1930s-1970s (Box 280)
- Department of State Education Officer files and correspondence, 1960s-1971 (Box 281)
- Clippings and other printed material related to USIA and current events, 1960s-1970s (Box 281)
- UNESCO printed material, 1960s-1970s (Box 282)
- World Affairs Council materials, 1949-1950s (Box 282)
  Including roster of attendees of 1955 conference, San Francisco
- University attendance files, including Stanford University, Harvard, and the University of California, Berkeley, 1920s-1970s (Box 283)
- Clippings on education in the U.S. (Box 283)
- UNESCO memos, 1960s-1970s (Box 284)
- Clippings, 1960s-1970s (Box 284-285.)
- Subject file on coexistence of the U.S. and USSR (Box 284-285.)
- Chinese Communism subject files, 1950s-1970s (bulk 1950s-1960s). (Box 286-288.)
  Includes typescript reports and holographic notes
- Red Guard materials (Box 286)
- Stanford and Harvard coursework, 1920s-1930s (Box 287-288.)
- UNESCO printed materials and reports, 1960s-1970s (Box 287-288.)
- UNESCO printed materials and reports, 1960s-1970s (Box 289)
- Class notes and papers, 1920s-1950s (Box 290)
- PhD coursework at University of California, Berkeley, notes and papers, 1940s-1950s (Box 290)
- High school chemistry lab notes, Oakland, California, 1922 (Box 290)
- UNESCO publication, 1972 (Box 290)
- USIA and Department of State Education Officer files, 1950s-1970s (Box 291)
- UNESCO subject files on international relations and on Latin America, 1960s-1970s (Box 291)
- "Han Language Phoeneticization Plan: Revised Draft," American Consulate General Hong Kong report, 1958 January 2 (in Italy subject folder) (Box 291)
- Professor Kerner speech to the Commonwealth Club of California on 1955 March 4 transcript and related printed materials (Box 291)
- Current Soviet strategy typescript letter, 1955 March 12 (Box 291)
- USSR subject files, 1930s-1970s (Box 292-293.)
- Research files and notes on Red Army and Soviet military, 1930s-1950s (Box 293)
- UNESCO printed materials, 1960s (Box 293)
- UNESCO files and printed materials, 1950s-1970s. (Box 294-295.)
  Includes unpublished reports, administrative files, itineraries for trips to Asia
- Subject files on the South Pacific, Central America, South America, and the Caribbean (Box 294-295.)
- Subject files on the Southeast Asia Treaty Organization (SEATO), Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG), and Southeast Asian Ministers of Education Secretariat (SEAMES) (Box 294-295.)
- Clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 296)
- Family snapshot photos developed in Taipei, Taiwan, undated (Box 297)
- Sound tape reel from American Committee for Liberation, 1657 Broadway, New York, NY, postmarked 1959 December 14, containing open reel with Radio Liberty NYPD label with holographic notation that reel contains "Hamlet - 3 soliloquies," time 18:13 (Box 297)
- UNESCO files, 1930s-1970s (bulk 1960s-1970s). (Box 297-300.)
  Includes typescript memos, correspondence, and holographic materials by Lowe, concerning Latin America, South America, Africa, and the Middle East, and materials related to Lowe's research trip to Africa,
- San Francisco black and white snapshots mainly showing sites and views commonly photographed, with negatives, May 1950 (Box 297-300.)
- USIS CAO Staff Farewell Party photos, Taipei, 1965 February 25 (Box 297-300.)
- Dr. Kuo Chi and family and others at Shehman Dam (Shihman Dam), black and white photos, 1965 February (Box 297-300.)
- Clippings, 1969-1981 (bulk 1978-1981) (Box 301)
- State Department bulletins concerning education, and regions or countries, 1969-1981 (bulk 1978-1981) (Box 301)
- Proposed op-ed on U.S. recognition of the People's Republic of China and "de-recognizing" the Republic of China on Taiwan for the San Francisco Chronicle and Examiner, 1978 December 17 (Box 302)
- Subject files, 1977-1980. (Box 302-303.)
  Mainly related to Chinese Communism, and also including subject files on Asia, Chinatown, and the Central Intelligence Agency
- Subject files related to investing, and international relations, including course notes and reports from Lowe's Harvard Business School studies, 1930s-1970s (Box 304)
- Subject files, mainly clippings, on Asia, Cambodia, and the Arab world, 1978-1981 (Box 304)
- Subject files related to investing, 1930s-1970s (bulk 1960s-1970s) (Box 305-306.)
- Subject files related to investing, 1960s-1970s (Box 307)
- UNESCO and USAID reports, 1970s (Box 307)
- Fu Jen University journal, Taipei, Taiwan, 1973 (Box 307)
- UNESCO reports, usually as photocopies, 1960s-1970s (Box 308-309.)
- State Department bulletins, 1960s-1970s (Box 308-309.)
- Department of State Office of Intelligence Research report "Chronology of Significant Events in the USSR for 1956,", 1957 (Box 308-309.)
- "Quarterly Review of Communist Propaganda Activities (April - June 1956),", undated (Box 308-309.)
- "Communist Use of Books, Pamphlets, and Periodicals for Propaganda Purposes,", 1957 (Box 308-309.)
- Chinese Christian Church of Greater Washington, D.C. files, 1969-1972, including material related to the Lowes' participation as members of the congregation, and church finances and missionary work, particularly regarding Asia (Box 310)
- Chinese Christian Fellowship, Mountain View, California materials, 1973 (Box 310)
- Research file on Japan and Taiwan, including notes, 1960s-1970s and undated (Box 310)
- Printed materials related to Taiwan and the Free China cause, 1960s-1970s (Box 310)
- Clippings and periodicals, 1970s (Box 310)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1960s-1970s. (Box 311)
  Contains mainly reports and periodicals related to UNESCO work, with some material from official government committees and non-governmental organizations in Taiwan (Republic of China) and Tokyo
- Clippings, 1976 (Box 311)
  Including a typescript copy of a letter to Anita and Patricia [Lowe], 1976 October 11, likely from Pardee Lowe
- Reports and periodicals on UNESCO, 1960s-1971 (Box 312)
- Draft reports, with edits, on UNESCO Youth Activities, 1968 and 1971 (Box 312)
- "UNESCO Youth Activities Program, 1951-1971," draft report (Box 312)
  1971 March 5
- Social Science Research Conference of the Pacific Coast files, 1930s (Box 312)
  including copy of "Proceedings and Minutes of the Third Annual Meeting of the Social Science Research Conference of the Pacific Coast," San Francisco, 1933 June 14, 15, 16, undated
  - Notes on the presentations, undated, probably 1933 June, with notes on panels that included anthropologists Paul Radin, Kroeber, and others (Box 312)
  - Copy of the provisional program for the 1935 meeting (Box 312)
- Publications related to Tatung University, Taipei, 1960s (Box 312)
- Subject files related to UNESCO work, 1960s-1970s. (Box 313-314)
  Mainly consisting of clippings.
  - Communist China (Box 313-314)
  - USSR (Box 313-314)
  - CIA (Box 313-314)
  - Foreign relations (Box 313-314)
  - Missile defense (Box 313-314)
  - Africa (Box 313-314)
  - Current events (Box 313-314)
  - Programs for youth (Box 313-314)
  - U.S. college campuses issues, including the environmental crisis, and student protests of the late 1960s (Box 313-314)
- Clippings relating to investing (Box 313-314)
- Ephemera relating mainly to San Francisco Chinatown, 1930s-1970s (Box 313)
  - "San Francisco Chinese Directory - Including Oakland-East Bay Section," San Francisco: Jimmy Lum Advertising Service, 1950 (Box 313)
- Bank of Canton materials, 1930s (Box 313)
  Including printed materials, typescript copies of letters from Bank of Canton Vice-President and Cashier G. B. Lau to Mr. Li, 1932 and 1935, with a detailed letter regarding the Bank of Canton's suspending payment pending reorganization, 1935 October 17
- Printed material. (Box 313)
  Includes clippings on New York and Bay Area sites such as China Camp, Marin, and China Beach San Francisco
- Holographic notes. (Box 313)
- Department of State memos from and to Lowe, 1969 (Box 314)
- UNESCO work files, 1960s-1970s (Box 315)
- State Department recruitment for a World Bank program, under agreement with UNESCO (Box 315)
- Educational development in less-developed countries materials, including lists of potential candidates for recruitment, 1964 and undated (Box 315)
- Subject files, educational development and recruitments, mainly consisting of clippings (Box 315)
- Subject files related to U.S. Policy on China and Taiwan, 1970s and undated (Box 315)
- "Old China Hand Name List," undated, annotated 1971 September 9, a list of home addresses or other contact info, likely by the State Department U.S. Information Service (Box 315)
- Subject files, comprised mainly of clippings, undated, 1930s. (Box 315)
  Includes a Harvard Business School report on the nitrate industry
- Subject files, natural resources and other investment topics, 1920s-1970s (Box 315)
- Free China Weekly issues, 1960s-1970s (Box 315)
- Subject files on Taiwan, including Department of State and U.S. Information Service (USIS) documents, and notes (Box 316)
  - U.S. policy on Taiwan (Box 316)
  - President Nixon's 1972 visit (Box 316)
  - Universities in Taiwan, 1960s-1970s (Box 316)
- Taipei International Women's Club materials, 1963-1964. (Box 316)
  Includes typescript, holographic, and printed material related to Mrs. Anita Lowe's work with the TIWC Educational and Cultural Committee and the Nursing Scholarship Sub-Committee Meeting
- Department of State Educational and Cultural Exchange Program files, 1940s-1970s. (Box 317)
  Consists mainly of files related to USIS work on the Educational and Cultural Exchange Program of the U.S. Department of State,
- USEF work in Shanghai typescripts, expense reports, and correspondence, 1949 (Box 317)
- "Recollection of the First United States Fulbright Educational Exchange Program in Mainland China," typescript memo recounting the history of the program from 1947 through 1965, 1971 April 22 (Box 317)
- Reports on USEF China program, 1958-1964 (Box 317)
- Printed materials related to the USEF China program, including issues of SEEN, Sino-American Educational Exchange News, published monthly by the United States Educational Foundation in the Republic of China, 1962 (Box 317)
  Also includes clippings on Youth, 1930s-1960s; and issues of Free China Weekly, 1970
- Chinese and Chinese American history and sociology project files, 1930s. (Box 318-319)
  Consists mainly of files related to Professor Richard T. LaPiere's sociological fiction manuscripts.
- Chinese and Chinese American history and sociology project correspondence, 1930s (Box 318-319)
  Related to Lowe serving as technical advisor on traditional Chinese and Chinese American culture and life in San Francisco Chinatown, and advising on manuscript from literary standpoint
- Son of Han (New York and London: Harper and Brothers, 1937), typescript manuscripts of Lapiere's novel (Box 318-319)
- "Golden Mountain," manuscript, undated, probably 1930s (Box 318-319)
- Son of Han publicity materials, including typescript, holographic, calligraphic, and printed materials (Box 318)
  - Son of Han store window display material (Box 318)
  - Printed materials (Box 318)
  - Oversize calligraphic banner (Box 318)
  - Printed broadside for a candidate for Miss Chinatown, 1939 (Box 318)
    In Chinese
- Missionary's fundraising letter regarding conditions in wartime China, and particularly Chungking, 1939 November 1 (Box 318)
- Institute of Pacific Relations, 1939 (Box 318)
  Study meeting materials, Virginia Beach, Virginia, 1939
- Clippings and other ephemera (Box 318)
- San Francisco Chinatown wedding invitations and event flyers, 1974 (Box 318)
- UNESCO work printed materials and reports, 1960s-1970s (Box 318)
- Free China Weekly issues, 1971 (Box 318)
- Correspondence with Cass Canfield, president of Harper and Brothers, and members of Canfield's staff, in Lowe's role of technical advisor and assistant to Professor LaPiere, 1936-1937 (Box 319)
- State Department files, 1940s-1970s (Box 320-322.)
- U.S. Educational Fund (USEF), in China file, 1947-1948 (Box 320)
  Including hiring letter from Leighton Stuart, Chairman, Board of Directors, United States Educational Foundation in China, 1948 January 9
- UNESCO work files, 1960s-1970s. (Box 321)
  Includes Department of State's Report of the Task Department of State Research Review Procedures for the Social and Behavioral Sciences and Other Educational Activities, including covering the issue of social science research carried out under the National Defense Education Act, 1967, undated
- Military training application letters, 1940 (Box 321)
- Subject files, including ephemera related to Washington, DC, area, 1940s (Box 321)
- Patricia Lowe schoolwork, Grade 6, 1971 (Box 321)
- Sino-American Trade writings with some clippings, 1940, 1939-1941 (Box 322)
- UNESCO work files, including memos from Lowe, 1960s-1970s (Box 322)
- "What Does the U.S. Get Out of UNESCO?" report preparation materials, 1968 (Box 322)
- Clippings, 1972-1973 (bulk 1973) (Box 322)
- UNESCO work reports and printed materials, 1970s (Box 323)
- Clippings, 1972 (Box 323)
- Patricia Lowe, grade school work, 1972 November 20 (Box 323)
- Subject files related to Chinatown and Chinese Americans, including related to professional options open to Chinese Americans, and the cultural heritage and restaurant industries, 1920s-1980s (Box 324)
- Clippings, ephemera, and some correspondence and notes, 1920s-1980s (Box 324)
- Chinese food industry in U.S. and restaurant business in San Francisco Chinatown files (Box 324)
- Letter from Lowe to George [likely George Chow], 1956 May 26, which relays a market analysis (Box 324)
- Results of a tasting dinner with friends Dick Young, former aid of General Stilwell, and Ernest Eng, former aid of General Marshall, to assess preferences among types of Chinese food by people not of Chinese descent (Box 324)
- Chinese restaurants in Washington, DC, and Taipei, Taiwan materials (Box 324)
- San Francisco Chinatown restaurants, 1930s-1960s (Box 324)
  Ephemera from Shanghai Low, Jade Palace, The Mandarin, Forbidden City, and Kan's; and 1960s menu from Ming's, Palo Alto, California
- San Francisco Chinatown files. (Box 324)
  Includes ephemera, 1930s
  - Golden Gate International Exposition on San Francisco's Treasure Island marketing of San Francisco Chinatown, 1939 (Box 324)
  - San Francisco Chinatown Illustrated tourist map by William Hoy's California Chinese Pioneer Historical Society, 1939 (Box 324)
- Clippings on urban redevelopment projects, 1960s (Box 324)
- Subject files on San Francisco Chinatown and Chinese American life, 1930s-1970s (Box 325-328.)
  - Lowe's public lecture files, 1936-1937, undated (Box 325-328.)
  - Collected materials related to the depression-era relief work of the Community Chest of San Francisco, 1930s (Box 325-328.)
  - Correspondence (Box 325-328.)
  - "Survey of Social Work Needs of the Chinese Population of San Francisco, Presented by the Committee to Study Social Welfare Needs of the Chinese Community, Mr. Barton T. Bean, Chairman, Miss Hilda Steinhart, Vice-Chairman," report by Community Chest of San Francisco Social Work Department, 1930 March 19 (Box 325-328.)
  - "Chinatown Social Welfare Agencies 1934," Lowe's hand-drafted organizational chart, depicting relations of governmental and non-governmental organizations, from F.E.R.A. [Federal Emergency Relief Agency] at top through San Francisco and San Francisco Chinatown agencies and organizations to named individuals (Box 325)
- Printed material, 1920s-1930s (Box 325)
  - Survey Graphic, "East By West - Our Windows on the Pacific," 1926 May 1, Volume IX Number 2 (Box 325)
  - Chinese Digest, 1935-1937 (Box 325)
  - Ruth Asawa's San Francisco Fountain, undated, probably 1973 (Box 326)
  - The Chinese Christian Student, 1933 (Box 326)
- Correspondence, Albert Lee and others, 1945-1953. (Box 325-328.)
  Mainly letters to Lee in Boston or Tokyo, and from Lowe in Shanghai or San Francisco, 1945-1953, with some additional Shanghai correspondents also represented. Includes photos
- San Francisco Chinese Counsel General files, 1933-1939. (Box 325-328.)
  Correspondence, briefings, reports, speech drafts, and printed ephemera related to assisting Chinese Consul General Chihtsing Feng with diplomatic activities
  - Burma-China Road promotion (Box 325-328.)
  - U.S. visit of Paul Yu-Pin, 1939 (Box 325-328.)
  - Vicar Apostolic of Nanking and special envoy of the Chinese National Government Relief Commission (Box 325-328.)
  - Rice Bowl fundraising for relief of victims of war in China (Box 325-328.)
  - Golden Gate International Exposition (GGIE) publicity related to the international relations goals, 1939 (Box 326)
  - Speeches written for the Chinese Consul for events broadly related to 1939 GGIE (Box 326)
  - Radio broadcast on 10-10 Celebration, 1939 October 10 (Box 326)
  - Chinese Consul files include file on wartime propaganda, featuring Dr. Margaret Chung, 1939 (Box 326)
- China Society of the Pacific Coast files, 1930s, undated. (Box 326)
  Includes meeting notes, correspondence, and drafts of governing documents exploring the formation of institute or organization for promoting mutual understanding and goodwill between China and the United States, and developing and promoting knowledge of the history of San Francisco Chinatown, to be called the China Society of the Pacific Coast, 1934, undated
- "World Friendship and Manchuria," speech, 1933 March 26 (Box 326)
- Draft writings, 1920s-1970s, undated, probably 1930s. (Box 326)
  Includes holographic notes and typescript draft
- "Death A Commonplace in Chinatown," undated, probably later 1930s. (Box 326)
  Includes research file
- State Department files, 1962-1965. (Box 326)
  Includes some ephemera related to Lowe's role as cultural attaché in Taipei, Taiwan
- Subject files (Box 327-328.)
  - Interracial relations, 1930s (Box 327-328.)
  - Social pathologies and juvenile delinquency, 1935 (Box 327-328.)
    Includes correspondence and detailed reports from California State institutions, including mental
- World War II China Theater service files, 1940s (Box 327-328.)
  - Memos, receipts, and other materials from Chungking, Shanghai, Shoochow, and Shanghai, and India (Box 327-328.)
  - Wartime newspapers in Chinese, 1944-1945, undated (Box 327-328.)
  - New Dehli, India, map, holographic copy, marked 1944 September 17 (Box 327-328.)
- Institute of Pacific Relations files, 1937-1940, undated. (Box 328)
  Includes typescript minutes, secretariat reports, writings, and correspondence, and typescript reports
- Guggenheim Memorial Foundation fellowship project proposal files, 1930s (Box 328)
  Includes a letter of application, with detailed biographical material, and a project proposal, 1935 December 15
- Clippings, 1930s-1970s (Box 328)
- Whites-only cemeteries still extant in the United States, as affecting nonwhite soldiers killed in action, 1951 (Box 328)
- Father and Glorious Descendent clippings and correspondence, 1943 and 1968 (Box 328)
  - Research and writing files, 1930s-1980s. (Box 329)
    Includes clippings, 1930s-1970s (bulk 1938-1950s)
  - "The Japan that Can Say No," English translation of Morita, Akio and Shintaro Ishihara's 1989 essay, undated (Box 329)
  - GGIE Pacific House planning files, 1935-1939, undated. (Box 329)
    Includes correspondence and biographical information
  - Chinatown Study Model for Saturday Evening Post story writing file, 1945, undated, probably 1930s. (Box 329)
    Includes holographic and typescript notes, writing draft, and writings by others. Also includes Jin Shan Shi Bao printed flyers promoting 39th anniversary Miss Chinatown contestants, in Chinese, undated, probably 1930s
  - Draft writings, 1936, undated, probably 1930s. (Box 329)
    Includes clippings and correspondence with magazine editors, 1934-1939
  - Institute of Pacific Relations, 1939 study meeting files, 1935, 1939-1940. (Box 329)
    Includes planning documents, printed material, and Chinese-language documents from China Institute of Pacific Relations, Hong Kong. Also includes Lasker, Bruno, "Changing Standards of Living in South China as Affected by Overseas Migration," Institute of Pacific Relations, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1935 April 16-24
  - Latin America clippings file, 1989-1990. (Box 329)
    Includes State Department bulletins
  - South Korea clippings file, 1989-1990. (Box 329)
  - New York Chinatown, 1970s. (Box 329)
    Includes movie flyers
- Subject files, 1980s-1990 (bulk 1988-1990). (Box 330)
  Consists mainly of clippings and other printed material such as State Department bulletins
  - Fulbright program (Box 330)
  - Hong Kong (Box 330)
  - Intelligence (Box 330)
  - Japan (Box 330)
  - Communist China (Box 331)
  - Education (Box 331)
  - Europe (Box 331)
  - West Germany (Box 331)
  - Red China surveys, 1981-1988. (Box 331)
    Includes a private report on a visit to China by expatriate C. H. Lowe, 1985, and unidentified notes related to trips to China in 1981-1984, undated
- Writing files, 1930s-1980s. (Box 332)
  - Writings related to "The Sian Incident" of 1936 December, Xi'an, China (Box 332)
    - "The 'Sian Incident' Formed Today's Oriental Policies" This World, 1938 January 30 (Box 332)
    - "Chiang's Kidnappers - Were They Traitors or Patriots?" This World, 1938 February 6 (Box 332)
    - "The Sian Affair: China's Indirect Declaration of War against Japan," typescript, undated, probably 1937 (Box 332)
    - Proposal by Lowe for an American Commission for Relief in China modeled after the American Relief Administration European Children's Fund, undated (Box 332)
  - Father and Glorious Descendant files, 1942-1943, 1965, 1968 (Box 332)
    - Reports of expenses and remittances, 1942-1943 (Box 332)
    - Reviews (Box 332)
    - Letter of congratulations from Fulbright grantee Thomas Lawton, 1965 February 12 (Box 332)
    - Harper's correspondence regarding potential sequel, 1968 (Box 332)
  - Richard LaPiere novels business documents, 1940s (Box 332)
  - Receipt for shipment, on behalf of Wah Chang Trading Corp., of portable typewriter to I. M. Pei, 1941 June 19 (Box 332)
  - "Chinatown Goes Forth to War,", 1938-1941. (Box 332)
    Includes correspondence with potential publishers, clippings, and receipts for donations to China War Relief Association of America
- Clippings and research materials, 1930s-1980s. (Box 332)
  - Course notes and clippings related to unemployment in U.S., 1930s (Box 332)
  - Clippings, 1941-1942 (Box 332)
  - Writings by others, 1956, 1981 and undated (Box 332)
  - Clippings on San Francisco Chinatown, Chinese immigration, and Communist China, 1989 (Box 332)
- Subject files, Universities, revolts, 1950-1971 (bulk 1960s). (Box 333)
  Includes Columbia University and the University of California
- Harvard Alumni Club files, 1947-1970s (Box 333)
  - Harvard Alumni Club of Shanghai printed material, 1948 (Box 333)
  - Alumni Directory, Harvard Club of the Republic of China, Taipei, Taiwan, 1961 (Box 333)
- UC Berkeley Institute of Slavic Studies PhD files, 1950s-1960s. (Box 333)